A Finding Aid to the Millard Sheets Papers, 1907-1990, in the Archives of American Art AAA.sheemill
Archives of American Art
Millard Sheets papers
1907-1990
AAA.sheemill
Archives of American Art
23 Linear feet
The Millard Sheets papers comprise 23 linear feet of material dating from 1907 to 1990 with bulk dates spanning 1956 to 1981. The collection documents Sheets's career as a designer, painter, and muralist, and his personal and professional interests through correspondence, writings, lectures, printed material, drawings, slides, photographs, and ephemera.
Sheets, Millard
Biographical Note
"Your painting is a measure of your mind"-Millard Sheets
Millard Sheets, as one of the founding members of the "California Scene Painters," exerted a lasting influence upon subsequent generations of Western painters. He and the small group of painters who worked in California during the 1930s and 1940s, developed a new style of watercolor painting that was at the forefront of the American watercolor movement of the time, and that later gave rise to a subsequent generation of painters who became known as the California Regionalist school.
Sheets was born in Pomona, California on June 24, 1907. His mother died in childbirth, and his father, John Sheets, unprepared to raise a baby alone, sent Millard to Pomona, California to be raised by his maternal grandparents, Lewis and Emma Owen. Sheets's grandfather proved to be a guiding force in his life, and when Sheets's father remarried and offered Millard the opportunity to return to the Sheets household, Millard chose instead to remain with his grandparents.
Sheets's love of horses can be directly traced back to his childhood years spent living at his grandfather's horse ranch. Millard rode his first horse when he was three years old. Throughout his life, Sheets returned to the theme of horses in his paintings, as well as maintaining a private stable of horses, and raising and breeding racehorses.
His interest in art also began in childhood. When he was still a young boy, his two maternal aunts encouraged him to play with crayons and pencils. Sheets took his first painting lesson from a neighbor at the age of seven, and by 1919 he had already submitted artwork to the copy division of the Los Angeles County Fair fine arts show competition. He submitted a drawing he had copied of a tinted photograph of Lake KIlarney, California. Sheets won first prize in his division.
It was through this competition that Millard met Theodore B. Modra, a Polish artist who had retired to the Pomona area. After giving Sheets a lecture on the evils of copying art, Modra offered to give him art lessons.
Sheets continued to pursue his interest in art and enrolled in the Choinard School of Art in Los Angeles, California. By the time that he graduated in 1929, Sheets had also managed to come to the attention of Dalzell and Ruth Hatfield of the Dalzell Hatfield Galleries in Los Angeles, California. The Hatfields were one of the most influential art dealers in Southern California, and that same year, they sponsored Sheets in his first one-man exhibition in 1929. The exhibition brought Sheets to the attention of Western Coast art critics and launched Sheets on his painting career.
In 1929 Sheets also learned that he had won second place in the annual Edgar B. Davis art competition held in San Antonio, Texas. The award came with a cash prize and Sheets made plans to travel to Europe to study and paint. Shortly before his departure, however, he met an art student, Mary Baskerville, and they began a whirlwind romance. With Baskerville's enthusiastic support for European plans, and with her promise that she would wait for him, Sheets departed for New York and then Europe.
While overseas during 1929 and 1930, Sheets studied under Dorfinant, a master printer in Paris. Through his work at this studio workshop, he met Henri Matisse.
Five months after Millard returned to the California in 1930, Sheets and Mary Baskerville married. Sheets worked as the director of the Fine Arts Exhibition of the Los Angeles County Fair. In 1932 Sheets returned to school to study art and humanities at Scripps College in Claremont, California. After graduating from Scripps, school officials approached Sheets with an offer to set up a separate fine arts program and asked him to chair the new department. This was the beginning of a twenty year association with the school. In 1938, he also became the Director of Art at Claremont Graduate School.
Sheets left the school during the years of World War II to serve as a war-time artist and journalist for Life magazine, and from 1943-1944 was stationed on the Burma-India Front. His experiences in Asia appeared to affect him deeply. In contrast to his earlier works which featured backgrounds with neutral tones and brilliant shades that highlighted and punctuated the compositions, the paintings from the wartime featured somber tones. Sheets remarked of this time:
Sheets returned from the war in 1944 and resumed his position at Scripps College until 1955 when he was approached by the Los Angeles County Board of Supervisors and asked to overhaul the fledgling Los Angeles County Art Institute. Sheets accepted the position and spent the next five years reshaping the mission and format of the school, renaming it the Otis Art Institute. In the years after Sheets left the directorship, the school eventually became part of the Parson's School of Design on the West Coast.
In 1953 Sheets founded the Millard Sheets Designs company. He hired between twenty-five and thirty artisans for large projects, with Susan Hertel, a former student of his, serving as his assistant in all the operations of the design studio. The working staff included engineers, registered architects, draftsmen, and artists, and the projects that the firm produced included murals, mosaics, stained glass, and sculpture for private homes and public and commercial businesses.
The design studio completed several major architectural projects throughout the late 1950s through the mid 1970s, including the design and construction of Cal Aero, a flight training school for the US Air Force, the National American Insurance Company offices for the California financier, Howard Ahmanson, Ahmanson Bank and Trust Company in Beverly Hills, many Home Savings and Loan Association Buildings, private residences, and the Scottish Rite Memorial Temples in Los Angeles and San Francisco, among many other projects.
Sheets also designed and completed mural and mosiac work for numerous public buildings in the Los Angeles area, as well as across the nation. Many of the murals and mosiacs were for those buildings designed by his firm while others were done as independent commissions.
In 1968 Sheets first proposed the murals he designed for the Los Angeles City Hall. His design was approved and he was awarded a commission to complete The Family of Man murals over the two main entrances to the Los Angeles City Hall. The murals were completed in 1971 and installed in 1972. Sheets also designed mosiacs and murals for the Mayo Clinic in Minnesota, the Library at Notre Dame University, the Scottish Rite Masonic Temple in Los Angeles, several Home Savings and Loan Association buildings in the Los Angeles area, the Detroit Public Library, and the Dome of the National Shrine of the Immaculate Conception in Washington, DC.
During the early 1960s Sheets participated in the American Specialist Program of the US Department of State. His first assignment was to Turkey in 1960, where he served as a visiting artist. The following year he went to the USSR in the same capacity.
During the early to mid 1950s Sheets became involved with Columbia Pictures and was technical advisor and production designer for a few years.
Millard Sheets was a member of the National Watercolor Society, the American Watercolor Society, the National Academy of Design, the Society of Motion Picture Art Directors, and the Century Association. Sheets actively promoted his own work and was a businessman, an active and prolific artist, instructor, and designer. Millard Sheets died on March 31, 1989 in Gualala, California.
Scope and Content Note
The personal papers of Millard Sheets (1907-1990) measure 23 linear feet and date from 1907-1990, with bulk dates of 1956-1981. The collection reflects Sheets's career as a designer, painter, and muralist, as well as his other personal and professional interests, through correspondence, writings, lectures, clippings, blueprints, drawings, slides, photographs, and ephemera.
The Project Files comprise the largest group of materials in the collection and document design work undertaken by Sheets through his company Millard Sheets & Associates Designs. Sheets and his associates produced concept drawings and blueprints and supervised the construction for a wide range of design projects that ranged in scale from architectural plans for private residences to bid proposals for shopping malls and financial institutions located in California and the Southwest.
Sheets designed interior and exterior plans for over forty Home Savings and Loan bank branches in California. The distinctive modular design which Sheets created and then customized by integrating interior and exterior art elements that highlighted local historical events or natural features became synonymous with the image of Home Savings and Loan. Sheets also teamed up with the architect Edward Durrell Stone to produce a proposal for the Capitol Mall Project, an urban renewal project for the Redevelopment Agency of the City of Sacramento. Researchers will find correspondence, job costs and billing statements, and notes that trace the development of these and other building construction projects. In some instances the documents are supplemented by blueprints, photographs, and/or drawings of the project, but in many cases, visual documentation is missing.
The Project Files also document work done by Millard Sheets on public projects such as the Family of Man mural in the Los Angeles City Hall Annex, a mosaic dome in the National Shrine of the Immaculate Conception, Washington, D.C., and the Word of Life mural at the University of Notre Dame, Ind., along with numerous other murals and mosaics created for private individuals and corporations.
The Correspondence Series primarily reflects the interaction between Sheets and his clients, colleagues, and personal acquaintances. These files will prove valuable to researchers who are interested in the way that Sheets's beliefs about the role of art in everyday life impacted the way he conducted business and managed both large and small design projects. The correspondence also reflects Sheets's interest in popular American culture, travel, political issues of the day, and art collecting.
The Membership Files document the wide variety of interests that Sheets maintained through active membership in associations and organizations. The material in this series consists primarily of correspondence, minutes of meetings, and notes which Sheets created or used as he served as a board member or trustee on a number of organizational boards, such as the California Institute of the Arts, the Claremont Colleges, Virginia Steele Scott Foundation, Webb School of California, and Goodwill Industries of Southern California.
Also found in this series is material that documents his interest and participation in various recreational and professional organizations. Sheets maintained a long association with the Economic Roundtable, a group of businessmen who met regularly to give presentations and share discussion on contemporary political and social issues. Sheets was a frequent speaker and his talks given at the Economic Roundtables can be found in Lectures and Speeches, a subseries of the Writings Series.
Included in the Millard Sheets & Associates Designs, Inc. series are records that reflect the day-to-day operations of Sheets's design firm. Found here are chronological copies of correspondence that were sent out, files Sheets maintained on various independent contractors that the design firm frequently used, resumes and letters of recommendation that Sheets received regarding potential employees, as well as records relating to the cost and maintenance of Sheets's office building.
The Teaching and Workshop Files document the instructional activities undertaken by Sheets throughout his career in the arts. Although Sheets became pivotal in establishing a regionally recognized art department at Scripps College in Claremont, California, the files that reflect his academic position there are limited in scope and depth. Researchers will find more substantive the files that he maintained on the numerous art demonstrations and paintings workshops that he conducted privately throughout his career. Sheets traveled extensively around the world through his teaching activities and the files in this series track his path.
Closely related to the Teaching and Workshop Files is the Painting Trips series. The material in these files document Sheets's service as an American Specialist in the Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs of the USIS, Department of State. Sheets served two times as a cultural arts representative in Turkey in 1960 and in the former USSR in 1961. Sheets also made numerous trips to South East Asia, which had proved an area of fascination for him since his experiences as a war correspondent in Burma and India in World War II. The files in this series document his painting trips to Tahiti, the Pacific Ocean Rim, and Hawaii. Also found are files that detail his painting activities in Mexico.
The Exhibition Files reflect the records that Sheets maintained regarding his participation in art exhibitions, as well as his files on art shows that he personally directed or organized for public or private groups or organizations. Although Sheets exhibited his work predominantly in the West and Southwest, the files in this series demonstrate that he exhibited both nationally and internationally as well.
Also found within the records for this series are files relating to Sheets's representation of his artwork through established galleries and art agents. The Dalziel Hatfield Galleries of Los Angeles, California, served as his primary agent for most of his painting career. Correspondence between Sheets and the Hatfields provide insight into Sheets's development into a regionally and nationally significant watercolorist and painter. The files relating to the Kennedy Galleries in New York and the Circle Gallery in Chicago reflect Sheets's efforts to maintain a national presence in the arts community.
The Jury Files document Sheets's involvement as a juror in regional, as well, as national shows. The files reveal the great variety of professional watercolor and painting exhibitions in which Sheets participated as either a jury panelist or solo judge.
The Writings Files provide an excellent source for researchers interested in Sheets's philosophical beliefs about the relationship between art and everyday life. His articles, lectures, and speeches predominantly address the role of the artist, the relationships that exist between artists and the community, and the role that art can play in making a fuller, more productive life. Also found in the files of this series are articles written by others about Sheets.
The Biographical Material series provides a short introduction to Millard Sheets. The files consist of the calendars maintained by Sheets and his wife and staff, which were used to coordinate his many commitments and appointments. Also found in the files of this series are family chronologies that were created by Mary Baskerville Sheets. Medical records and resumes provide personal information about Sheets's background and health. A small file of military memorabilia provides information about Sheets's contributions to the war effort in World War II.
The Printed Matter series documents family activities and personalities through publicity clippings. Also found are exhibition catalogs and announcements that Sheets saved regarding other artists. Miscellaneous interests and activities of Sheets are found through magazine articles, brochures, and flyers.
The Photographs series includes photographic documentation for Sheets's artwork, horses, and major projects. A small group of photographs of Sheets are also in this series.
The files in the Artwork series include original drawings by Mary Baskerville Sheets and Millard Sheets.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into fourteen series. Small series, such as Biographical Material are generally based on type of document. Larger series, such as Correspondence or Project Files, are arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent or project. General correspondence has been made into its own series, but other series or subseries may also contain some correspondence. Within particular series, materials have been further divided into subseries which represent particular aspects of the project or event. For example, the Writings Series is further divided into subseries of books and articles, eulogies, and lectures and speeches. An outline listing series and subseries titles and dates follows.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1907-1982, undated (boxes 1-2; 1.25 linear ft.)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1929-1990, undated (boxes 2-4; 2.75 linear ft.)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, 1933-1980, undated (boxes 5-6; 1.25 linear ft.)
Series 4: Membership Files, 1946-1982, undated (boxes 6-8; 2.5 linear ft.)
Series 5: Millard Sheets & Associates Designs, 1934-1982, undated (boxes 8-9; 1.0 linear ft.)
Series 6: Project Files, 1956-1981, undated (boxes 9-18; 8.25 linear ft.)
Series 7: Teaching and Workshop Files, 1932-1982 (box 18; 0.5 linear ft.)
Series 8: Painting Trips, 1959-1980, undated (box 18; 15 folders)
Series 9: Exhibition Files, 1932-1937, 1951-1988, undated (box 19; 0.75 linear ft.)
Series 10: Jury Files, 1941-1982 (boxes 19-20; 42 folders)
Series 11: Writings, 1936-1988, undated (boxes 20-22; 2.5 linear ft.)
Series 12: Printed Matter, 1936-1922, undated (boxes 22-23; 20 folders)
Series 13: Photographs, 1934-1983, undated (box 23; 16 folders)
Series 14: Artwork, circa 1929, undated (box 23; 2 folders)
Provenance
The collection was donated to the Archives of American Art in 1992 by Mary B. Sheets, Millard's widow. Millard Sheets loaned a small amount of material for microfilming in 1965.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on microfilm reels 5676-5707 and for interlibrary loan.
Dalzell Hatfield Galleries; Millard Sheets & Associates Designs; Sheets, Mary Baskerville; Art and society; Art--California; Art--Philosophy; Art--Study and teaching; Designers--California; Horses--Breeding; Muralists--California; Photographs; Slides (photographs); Watercolorists--California
- Biographical Material, 1907-1982, undated; Series 1; (boxes 1-2; 1.25 linear ft)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains a variety of types of documents, including award certificates, appointment calendars, chronologies, resumes, clippings, and medical, governmental, and military records. The appointment calendars will be of particular interest to researchers since they document the complex scheduling that was required to keep Sheets aware of the numerous deadlines, meetings, and teaching commitments that made up his daily routine. Multiple copies of calendars reflect the system used to keep his staff and family aware of his whereabouts and activities on any particular day, especially since Sheets maintained several residences and work locations.
  Arrangement note
  The files are arranged chronologically.
  - Awards, 1973-1981 (Box 1, Reel 5676)
  - Biographical text, undated (Box 1, Reel 5676)
  - Birth certificate and social security card, 1907, 1942 (Box 1, Reel 5676)
  - Calendars, 1965-1981; (11 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5676)
  - Family chronologies, undated (Box 2, Reel 5676)
  - Family memorabilia, 1929, 1945-1992, undated (Box 1, Reel 5676)
  - Medical records, 1966-1980; (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5676)
  - Resumes, 1961-1976 (Box 1, Reel 5676)
  - World War II memorabilia, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Reel 5676)
- Correspondence, 1929-1990, undated; Series 2; (boxes 2-4; 2.75 linear ft.)
  The letters in these files primarily reflect the variety of Sheets's business and social interests throughout his design and art career. Among the correspondents may be found architects, design professionals, business and bank executives, professors, art collectors, and racehorse owners and managers. Topics covered include discussion of design projects, travel, horse breeding, art and urban planning. Researchers will find the letters between Millard Sheets and his wife, Mary Baskerville Sheets, during his World War II service in Asia and the Pacific Rim, to be of particular interest. Their correspondence document the details of Sheets's travel and wartime experience as a staff artist and war correspondent for Life.
  The files are arranged alphabetically by correspondent, and then chronologically within each folder.
  - Ahmanson, Howard and Caroline, 1956, 1960-1968, 1985, undated (Box 2, Reel 5676)
  - Alvin, Joe, 1962-1978 (Box 2, Reel 5676)
  - American Artist, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Reel 5676)
  - Aubin, Philip T., 1964 (Box 2, Reel 5676)
  - "A" miscellaneous, 1943-1946, 1963-1984, undated; (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5676-5677)
  - Blair, Barbara, 1966, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Bowles, John and John R. Bowles, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Brown, Edmund G., 1964 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Bullock's, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - "B" miscellaneous, 1964-1978, undated; (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Cabalgata Mexicana, Palm Springs, Calif., 1969-1977 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Childs, Kenneth D., 1959, 1961-1970, undated (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Colclough, Phyllis, 1967-1978 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Courtright, Hernando, 1961-1978 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Crain, E. Gene, 1969-1978 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Cruickshank, Charlaleo (Mrs. F. G.), 1965-1967 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - "C" miscellaneous, 1929, 1964-1979, undated; (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Dalzell Hatfield Galleries, Los Angeles, Calif., 1964-1975 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Dieterle, William and Charlotte, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Dorn, Warren M., 1964 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - "D" miscellaneous, 1964-1978, undated (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - d'Estournelles de Constant, Vivien, 1974-1977, undated (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - "E" miscellaneous, 1964-1980, undated (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Family members, 1929, 1989, undated (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Fine Arts Rental Gallery, Claremont, Calif., 1963-1964, undated (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - "F" miscellaneous, 1963-1978, undated (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - General Adjustment Bureau, Pomona, Calif., 1965-1966 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Gonzales, Emilio O., 1976 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
    (regarding treatment at Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minn.)
  - Graham, Harold E., 1966 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - "G" miscellaneous, 1929, 1964-1981, undated; (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Hebald, Milton, 1964 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Hertel, Susan, 1982 (Box 2, Reel 5677)
  - Hirsch, Clement L., 1963-1964 (Box 2, Reel 5678)
  - Hirsh, Mr. & Mrs. Allan M., Jr., 1965-1971 (Box 2, Reel 5678)
  - Holmes, Milton, 1964-1969, undated (Box 2, Reel 5678)
  - "H" miscellaneous, 1964-1979, undated; (2 folders) (Box 3, Reel 5678)
  - "I" miscellaneous, 1965-1976 (Box 3, Reel 5678)
  - "J" miscellaneous, 1964-1975 (Box 3, Reel 5678)
  - Kapousouz, Vasileos, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Reel 5678)
  - Kristiania Kunst & Metalstøberi, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Reel 5678)
  - Kubly, Don (Art Center College of Design, Pasadena, Calif.), 1978-1979 (Box 3, Reel 5678)
  - "K" miscellaneous, 1943, 1964-1978 (Box 3, Reel 5678)